



The SIR model is a very powerful tool (no doubt) but it was developed a century ago when the scientific paradigms were different.
Looking today at SIR with a critical eye immediately shows that it suffers from some approximations that limit its ability to represent reality.
I mean:
1) SIR is a linear model and nature is anything but linear. (INSERT THE VIDEO HERE)
2) The 'R' in 'SIR' means 'Recovered' and doesn't matter if the person is healed or died!
3) spread of a disease can have waves (the covid had waves). The SIR model, at least the common representation, cannot have waves. It always results in an exponential evolution of the desease. In fact, the structure of the reasoning underlying the SIR model is the same used to define the behavior of a capacitor or an inductor. In both cases, the evolution of the electrical parameter in these two objects follows the same exponential evolution. The waves only appear when these two electrical devices are connected together. For me, this is the evidence that the SIR model is missing something very important.
(There are many examples in nature of "systems" that can have "waves" and they all have two elements each acting "against" the other:
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscillazione)

After a century SIR is squeezed like a lemon, but its limitations still remain. Perhaps, new ways to tackle the same problem will lead to new solutions. So, I believe, there is enough room to think about other complementary models. 
My try was to develop an application (c#) to model the reality defing:
- a region (a selected surface, for example, a city;) 
- People that move over the region. 
- a disease (CoViD for example) 

A disease contaminates an area (a point in the region), when someone moves over the area gets infected and after a short latency becomes ill (purple dot in the GUI's left panel). The infected person, sneezing and touching, contaminates other points over the region. After a while, the person recovers. 

To let the model better adere to reality there are also other entities that act like 'accumulation points': schools; hospitals, and offices. 

Even the evolution of the virus into an infected body was modeled avoiding the SIR equations. In this case, to make things easy, evolution is an array of values. The evolution should be provided by virologists. (One first result shows that the disease's spread is tightly correlated with the topology, instead of the characteristics of the virus.)
